SGS曙光社字幕组
"I always have the feeling that I'm losing something," she said.
いつも何かを失う予感があると　彼女はそう言った
翻译：卡卡罗特 Kangaroo
时间：ACG
特效：Teny
后期：小怡
I was just a middle school student at that time.
当時ー
まだ中学生だった僕には実感が持てるはずもなかったけれど
So, I couldn't possibly understand what she meant.
But still...
それでも　彼女のその言葉は　不思議に僕の心を震わせた
Her words moved me.
It was before the war...
まだ戦争前ー
...when the huge island called Ezo was still a foreign territory.
エゾと呼ばれた巨大な島が
他国の領土だった頃の話だ
Amazing!
すごーい！
An airplane!
ヒコーキ！？
On that day long ago...
今はもう遠いあの日　あの雲のむこうには
...beyond those clouds...
...lies the place of our promise.
彼女との約束の場所があった
云之彼端   约定之处
"In your delirious fever, panting,
you asked me for the last bowl of snow...
“はげしいはげしい熱やあえぎの間から”
March, Tsugaru County, Aomnori Prefecture
“おまえはわたくしに頼んだの”
...that fell from the sky, the galaxy, the sun, the atmospheric strata...
“銀河や太陽 気圏などと呼ばれた世界の”
“空から落ちた雪の最後のひとわんを”
Between two pieces of granite sleet makes a solitary puddle.
“ふた切れのみかげ石材に”
“みぞれはさみしくたまっている”
I stand on them, precariously...
“わたくしはその上に危なく立ち”
...keeping the pure, white, two-phased balance of snow and water...
“雪と水との真っ白な二相系をたもち”
...and get for my gentle sister her last food..."
“すきとおる冷たいしずくに満ちた”
In those days, we admired two things.
あの頃  僕たちは二つのものに憧れていた
How much longer?
あと何分ー？
We still have time.
まだ大丈夫よぉ
Here.
Note: South Yomogita
ほら
That's hot!
アチッ…  サンキュー
Thank you.
Hiroki, when do you work next?
ヒロキ  次バイトいつ行く？
Well, I've got club activities today and tomorrow...
ああ  明日まで部活だから  あさってかな？　タクヤは？
So, maybe the day after.
How about you, Takuya?
Tomorrow morning's my last day of training too.
俺も明日の朝練で最後だから
Then it's decided, the day after tomorrow, okay?
あさってで決まりな
Okay.
ああ
Note: Bus U-Turn Area; Other vehicles not allowed to park here.
- Yomogita Village; Traffic Department
One of the things that we admired was our classmate, Sawatari Sayuri.
憧れの一つは同級生の沢渡サユリで
And the other...
そしてもう一つは
...was that enormous tower that rose beyond
the border on the other side of the Tsugaru Strait.
津軽海峡を挟んだ国境のむこうにそびえる　あの巨大な塔
I didn't know how to solve that problem at all.
I was always looking up at that tower.
いつだって僕はあの塔を見上げていた
So, I asked the teacher, and...
And?
I felt something very important to me was waiting there.
僕にとって　とても大切なものが
あの場所には待っている気がした
I was filled with yearning.
とにかく　気持ちが焦がれた
Note: Welcome to this peaceful village
Someday...
…いつか！
Someday, I will go there.
…いつか
絶対に行くんだ
Shirakawa-senpai!
白川センパイ！
We'll go on ahead.
先　行ってるぜ
Yeah.
ああ　悪い
Sorry.
あ　あの　センパイたち今日で引退だから
Well, you seniors are retiring today, so...
There's something we'd like to give you.
わたしたいモノあるんです
Go on, Kana-chan!
ほら　カナちゃん
What? H-Hey...
え　ちよ　ちよっと
あの
Well...
Here...
Note: To Shirakawa Takuya-senpai
…これ！
So, you turned her down?
…で　断ったのか？
Just like the others.
いつもみたいに
Yeah.
うん
First-year Matsuura, huh?
1年の松浦か　アイツかわいいのに
That's a shame. She's pretty cute.
Then, you go out with her, Hiroki.
じゃあ　ヒロキが付き合えよ
What?!
はァ？
Would you have hooked up with her?
お前だったら付き合うのか？
What? No!
え　イヤ　なんで俺が…
Why would I?
お前　誰か好きなヤツいるの？
You like someone else, is that it?
What? Why?
え　な　なんで？
No, well, I mean...
いや　まあ　確かにかわいい子だとは思うけどさ
I think she's cute and all, but...
I don't really know what to do when you're, uh, dating someone.
付き合うって　俺
何すればいいのか　よく分かんないしさ…
You're not the one she confessed to, you know?
お前が告白されたんじやないだろ
Hey, you asked!
お前が聞いたんだろ！
Sawatari...
沢渡…！
あ　藤沢君！
Fujisawa-kun!
Sawatari...
沢渡　帰り遅いんだな
You're going home late today.
Yeah.
うん　練習してたら遅れちやった
I'm running behind. I was practicing.
Violin?
バイオリン？
Yeah.
うん　藤沢君は白川君と一緒じゃないの？
Shirakawa-kun's not with you?
No.
ああ　俺も部活寄っててさ
I was practicing, too. For my club.
I notice you sometimes practice archery alone.
藤沢君　ときどき一人で弓引いてるね
え　あ　俺　下手だからさ…　雑念多いんだ
Oh, I'm not any good.
So, I get distracted easily.
Note: National Railways
Do you have any plans for spring break, Fujisawa-kun?
藤沢君春休み何か予定あるの？
Yeah.
うん　タクヤと一緒にバイトするんだ
Takuya and I have a part-time job lined up.
A job?
え　バイト？　いいなー　どこで！？
I'm so jealous! Where is it?
A factory in Hamana. They do subcontracting for the military.
浜名の軍事下請けの工場　誘導弾　組み立てたり
We'll be putting together guided missiles and stuff.
ふうん　すごいなあ　アルバイトなんて
It's great that you've got a job.
All I've got are my club activities...
私は部活くらいだな…
Oh, yeah?
そっか
Yeah.
うん
The next station is Nakaoguni, Nakaoguni.
次は中小国　中小国
After Nakaoguni, we'll stop at Oodaira.
中小国の次は太平に停車します
We're already at my station.
もう着いちゃう…
You know what?
…あのね　わたしきのうね
Last night, I had a dream that I would go home with you like this.
こうやって藤沢君と一緒に帰る夢　見たんだ
Bye-bye!
バイバイ！　また新学期ね！
I'll see you next semester!
あ　ああ…
Okay...
Meanwhile...
12日から3日間の日程で行われるー
...it appears tensions raised by
Japan's response to the North-South problem...
アメリカとユニオンの第11回閣僚級会談では
...will be the focus of the 11th Summit...
...a proposed three-day meeting between
America and the Union set to begin on the 12th.
緊張の続く日本の南北問題への対応が
焦点になる模様です
The Union government voiced deep concern...
三沢基地を始めとするアメリカの施設増強に
...regarding the reinforcement of
Misawa Base and other American facilities...
懸念を示すユニオン政府に対し
...while the American government
expressed apprehension that the Union...
アメリカ政府は　ユニオンがエゾ領に建造したー
...has yet to reveal the purpose of
the enormous Tower facility built in Ezo territory.
巨大な塔施設の目的を未だ明らかにしていないことに
強い不安感を示しています…
Hello!
こんにちはー
Alright!
やった　お茶の時間ですか
Tea time, huh?
Sure is. Come have a seat.
おう　こっち座れよ
Okay.
ハイ
You're late, Hiroki.
おせえよ　ヒロキ
Sorry.
ごめん
Hiroki, I heard what you did.
ヒロキ　聞いたぜ
You guys went and stole a Chukar target drone from the MSDF?
お前たち　海自のチャッカー盗んできたんだって？
Like I said...
だから
That's not true!
違いますよ
We didn't steal it.
盗んだんじやなくて
Note: Maritime Self Defense Force
We found it in Amagamori!
天が森で拾ったんですよ！
So, you stole it.
やっぱり盗んだんじゃねえか
Well, they are flying a lot of drones
in their training exercises these days.
まあ　最近はドローンを飛ばした訓練も多いから
I guess it will be all right.
大丈夫だろうけど
Just make sure they don't trace it back to you.
足がつかないように気をつけろよ
That's right.
そうそう
The Public Safety Commission already keeps an eye on this place.
タダでさえここは公安から　目ぇつけられてるんだから
Don't say things that could damage my reputation!
人聞きの悪いこと言ってんじゃねえよ！
Back to work! Work!
仕事しろ　仕事
Yes, sir.
うーす
See you later.
じゃあな
Okay.
ハイ
And you two... Starting tomorrow, you show up ready to work, okay?
お前たちも　明日からちゃんと働きに来いよ
I'll be workin' you for the cost of those materials and then some.
材料費以上に　コキ使ってやるからな
Yes, sir.
はい…
Well, then...
それじゃ　失礼します！
If you'll excuse us.
Okay.
オウ
There was a reason we started working.
僕たちがアルバイトを始めたのには理由があった
I heard that when Ezo was still called Hokkaido...
まだエゾが北海道と呼ばれ　この国の一部だった頃
...and it was still part of this country...
...there were plans to dig a tunnel under the Tsugaru Strait.
津軽海峡の下にトンネルを掘るという計画があったそうだ
It ended up being interrupted due to
the Separation between north and south...
結局　それは南北分断によって中断されたのだけれど
...but in the mountains around here, you can sometimes find...
このあたりの山中には
まだ工事の名残の廃駅やレールが所々残っている
...tracks and abandoned stations,
remnants of the old construction days.
Last year...
僕たちは　この山頂にあるそういう廃駅の一つで
We started building something in an
abandoned station at the top of this mountain.
去年から　あるモノを作っていた
Emishi Manufacturing does subcontracting for the US military...
米軍の下請け工場であるエミシ製作所で働くのは
...and we started working there, so we could buy parts for this thing.
そのパーツ代を稼ぐためだ
The place that looks so close, it's like you could reach out and grab it...
手が届くほどの距離に見えているのに
...but you can never actually get to.
行くことのできない　あの場所
We wanted to see it with our own eyes...
僕たちは　その見知らぬ島も　そこにそびえる巨大な塔も
...that strange island and the enormous Tower that rose from it.
どうしても目前に見てみたかった
A lot of the snow's melted away, huh?
だいぶ雪が減ったなあ　早く再開したいな
I'd like to get started again soon.
Here's hoping we don't get any more snow...
これでもう雪が降らなきゃね
In any case, we'd better try and get all the remaining materials.
とにかく　残りの材料揃えないと
We still don't have the exterior nanonet or the self-starting motor.
外装用のナノネットと
セルモーターも　まだ揃ってないし
Note: Hakamagoshi Tunnel
The superconducting motor's the main thing, right?
大物は超電動モーターだろ　最後にはケロシンも必要だし…
And we're also gonna need kerosene.
Even with this part-time job,
we may not be able to make enough money.
明日からのバイトだけじや　追いつかないかもな
Don't worry. It will work out.
何とかなるよ！　夏休みもあるしさ
There's always summer break.
Yeah, that's true.
そうだよな
We were planning to fly to that Tower beyond the border...
だから僕たちは
づエラシーラと名づけたこの飛行機で
...in this airplane we named Velaciela.
国境のむこうのあの塔まで飛ぼうとしていたんだ
That same dream again...
…また同じ夢…
Four Months Later, Early Summer
Sawatari!
沢渡？
Note: Quantum Gravity Theory; A Dictionary for Understanding Parallel Universes
- Katsuhiko Sato
Takuya-kun...
タクヤ君
So, anyway...
Um...
あのさあ
あの…
Oh, sorry.
あ　ごめん
That's okay.
ううん…
Hiroki-kun said...
You know, Hiroki said...
ヒロキがさ
ヒロキ君が
あ…
ふふっ…
We haven't talked that much, have we? Just the two of us.
…私たち二人だけで話したことって
あんまりなかったよね
Guess not.
そうかもな…
Takuya-kun, do you like physics?
ねタクヤ君物理好きなの？
What?
え？ああこの本？…ちょっと興味があってさ
Oh, this book?
Yeah, it's kinda interesting.
That's amazing.
すごいなー
They say my grandpa was a physicist.
わたしのおじいちやんもね　物理学者だったんだって
Really?
へえそっちのほうがすごいよ
That's more amazing.
I've never met him, though.
でも会ったことはないんだけどね
Because of the Separation?
南北分断？
Yeah.
うん
Oh, I see.
そっか…
The train bound for Hirosaki is arriving at Platform 3.
Hey. Do you guys still have that job?
ね　タクヤ君たち　今もアルバイトしてるんでしょ？
Is it fun?
楽しい？
I don't know.
どうかな…
It's run by this scary old man.
怖いオヤジの工場だからさ　怒鳴られるし　こき使われるし
He yells at us and makes us work hard.
Is he really that scary?
そんなに怖いの？
He's like a demon or something.
ねぶたの鬼みたいだぜ
Really?
ほんと？
You wanna come and see for yourself?
今度見に来るか？
Well...
え…
But won't I be in your way?
でも　ジャマじゃない？
No.
イヤ　ヒロキもきっと喜ぶからさ
I bet Hiroki will be happy to see you too.
Okay! I'll come by!
うん　行く行く！
The train bound for Kanita and Minmaya is arriving at Platform 2.
2番線　蟹田・三厩方面行き
下り電車が参ります
Please step back and wait behind the white line.
白線の内側までお下がりになって
お待ち下さい
Hey, Takuya-kun?
……ねえ　タクヤ君
This may sound strange, but promise that you won't laugh?
おかしな話かもしれないけど　笑わない？
え　なに？　笑わないよ
What is it?
I won't laugh.
Okay, I'll tell you.
じゃあ話すね　あのね……
Listen...
Why did you go and do something like that?
お前
なに勝手なことしてんだよ
What could I do?
しょうがないだろ…　そういう話の流れだったんだよ
The conversation just kind of went in that direction.
What do we do?
どうする
Do we tell her about flying to the Tower too?
塔まで飛ぶことも言っちやうか？
Bad idea.
そのことはマズイよ
Yeah.
だよなあ…　でも行き先聞かれたらどうする？
But what do we do if she asks us where we're going?
うーん…
Um...
あの…
Yes?
ハイ！？
…ハハハ…
…フフ…
あっ　こんにちはー
Hello.
Hey.
オウ　暑いな　今日は…
It's hot today, huh?
Hello.
こんにちは　おじゃまします
I hope you don't mind me stopping by.
Oh, sorry.
ヤ　スミマセン
Thanks for always looking after these two morons.
え　えーと　いつもウチのバカニ人が
お世話になってるみたいで…
So, about Okabe-san...
…岡部さんってさ
Do you think he's single?
独身だっけ？
Nah.
いや　バツイチって噂聞いたぜ
I heard a rumor that he's divorced.
Well, thanks so much.
Somehow that makes sense.
なーんか　分かる気がするなァ…
I didn't know there was a place like this here!
こんな場所があったんだー！　ひろーい
It's so big!
Amazing!
すごーい！
An airplane?
ヒコーキ！？
That's right.
そうだよ…
ハァ…
You two are building this yourselves?
これ　二人だけで作ってるの？
Yeah.
うん　2年の夏から少しづつやってるんだ
We've been working on it little by little
since our eighth grade summer vacation.
We've been working at that factory back
there to get parts and advice from Okabe-san.
さっきの工場でバイトしながら部品揃えて
岡部さんとかに相談しながらさ
Right?
なァ？
Yep.
うん
It's still far from complete though.
まだまだ未完成なんだけどね
It's amazing.
…すごいな…
Hey!
ね　ホントにすごい！
This is really amazing!
…あ　ありがとう…
Thanks.
Hey.
…ねえ
When do you think it will be done?
ヒコーキ　いつ頃完成するの？
We'd really like to finish it during summer vacation, but...
ホントは夏休み中に完成させたいんだけどさ
That's probably not gonna happen.
でもたぶん　無理だよ　まだまだ時間がかかりそうなんだ
It looks like it's gonna take a lot more time.
I guess we're shooting for finishing it before the end of the year.
まあ　年内が目標かなあ
Oh, I see.
そうかー……
Say, where are you going to fly it to?
ね　あのヒコーキで　どこまで行くの？
To the Tower.
あの塔まで行くんだ
あ…！
Tower?
塔ってユニオンの塔？
Do you mean the Union's Tower?
Yep.
うん
We think it will take about forty minutes to fly to the Tower.
塔までたぶん40分くらいで飛べると思うんだ
The real problem is how we're going to cross the border...
国境をどう越えるかが問題なんだけどね
...but we've got some ideas about that, too.
でもそれも考えがあるんだ
Amazing, amazing!
すごい　すごい　いいなァ　北海道！！
Hokkaido sounds great!
Do you wanna go too, Sawatari?
…沢渡も行くか？
What?
…え…いいの！？
Would that be okay?
Sure!
うん
Really?
本当？うん行く行きたい！
Okay, I'll go!
I really wanna go!
Wow! Thank you!
わあありがとう！！
But I don't know if it will even fly, though.
でも本当に飛べるか分からないぜ
Don't worry!
大丈夫きっと飛べるよ！
It will fly for sure!
Yeah!
うん
So, it's a promise, okay?
ねじゃあ約束！
Yeah.
ああ
It's a promise.
じゃあ約束な
Okay!
うん！
In those days, I felt that time,
that place would remain unchanged for the rest of my life.
あの頃は一生このまま
この場所この時間続く気がした
The Tower that stood beyond the clouds...
憧れていた　雲のむこうのあの塔は
...became an important promised place to me... A promised place.
Note: Ookawadai Shopping District
僕にとって　大切な約束の場所になった
In that moment, we weren't afraid of anything.
あの瞬間ー
僕たちには恐れるものなんて　何もなかったように思う
The truth was that the world history was changing.
本当は　すぐ近くで
世界や歴史は　動いていたのだけれど
But in those days, the smells of the night wafting into the train...
でもあの頃は
汽車に漂う夜の匂いや　友達への信頼や
...the trust I had in my friend...
...and the hint of Sayuri that lingered in the air...
空気をふるわすサユリの気配だけが
These were everything in the world to me.
世界のすべてだと感じていた
US-Japanese and Union forces clashed in a minor
armed conflict last night until just before dawn this morning.
昨晩から今朝未明にかけ
Note: File Footage; Union Air Force Plane
ARMED CONFLICT OFF TSUGARU STRAIT LAST NIGHT
津軽海峡沖から42.15線までの緩衝地域にかけて
Note: Yesterday, Tsugaru
The skirmish occurred in the buffer area
between the Tsugaru Strait and the 42nd latitude.
米日軍とユニオン軍の
小規模な武力衝突が行われました
Upon hearing this...
それを受け　警視庁は
...the Metropolitan Police Department announced
that they will deploy 3300 guards in Tokyo prefecture...
国内のウィルタ解放戦線などの
テロ組織によるー
...as a precaution against terrorist
activities directed toward the Union Embassy...
ユニオン大使館へのテロ行動を警戒するとして
...by organizations such as the Uilta Liberation Front.
三三〇〇人の警備要員を
都内に配備することを発表しました
Yeah.
おう
If you've got the money, I'll sell you kerosene or whatever...
そりゃ　お前ケロシンだって何だって
金払えば売ってやるけどさあ…
...but jet fuel's gonna be expensive.
でもジェット燃料は高いぜ
Why don't you just use a reciprocating
engine or a superconducting motor?
素直にレシプロか
超電導モーターにしといたらどうなんだ？
うーん…
You know how to do the rest?
あと分かるか？
Yes!
ハイ
All right. Take care of it.
ヨロシクな
Why do you wanna go through all
the trouble of using a jet engine anyway?
なあ大体なんでわざわざジェットエンジン便うんだよ？
'Cause it's cool!
カッコイイから！
That's the only reason?
それだけかよ？
Hold on a second!
ちょっと待てよ　他にもっと色々理由あっただろ
We had other reasons, right?
ええーつと…ああれだ
Let's see...
Oh, yeah! That one!
'Cause we were lucky enough to find it!
せっかく拾ったから！
That's not it!
違うだろー！
What was it?
何だっけホラ二重エンジンにした理由
Remember, the reason we made it a dual engine?
There was a good reason for it.
もっとちゃんとしたわけがあったんだよ
Oh, that's right!
ああれだ
'Cause we wanted it to transform!
変形させたいから
That's not it!
違うだろー！
Whatever... I don't care what it was.
…何でもイイけどさあ…
Just don't kill yourselves, all right?
お前たち　死ぬなよな…　面倒臭いから
It will be a hassle for me.
Oh, yeah, you two.
あー　お前ら　夏休み入ったらちゃんと毎日来いよ
Be sure to come here every day when summer vacation starts.
Yes, sir!
はーい…
So...
ねえホントに弾くの？
You really want me to play it?
Note: Only 6 more days until summer break!!
Friday, September 18 Day Duty: Kitamura Miki
Yeah.
うん放課後に行くからさ
We'll come see you after school.
Note: Music Room
I'm not that good, though.
ねーわたしあんまり上手じゃないよ
Don't worry.
大丈夫
I've never even seen someone play a violin.
俺そういうの目の前で見たことないんだ
Let me hear it.
聴かせてよ
I'd like to hear, too.
俺も聴きたいな
うーん…キンチョーするなあ…
I'm so nervous...
Nanonet doesn't reflect radar, right?
ナノネットはレーダーを反射しないんだろ？
But we'll be flying into the buffer area.
でも緩衝地帯を飛ぶんだぜ…いくらナノネットの外装でもさ
Nanonet trim or not...
If we aren't careful, the US military
will spot us even before the Union can.
ヘタに飛んだらユニオンより先にまず米軍に見つかるよ
Note: Dream Net
I guess we'll have to fly as low as possible...
やっぱりなるべく低く飛ぶしかないかー…
...so we can blend in with the waves and the contours of the land.
波と地形にまぎれてさ
If we leave early, we can use the morning haze as cover, too.
早朝に出れば朝モヤにも隠れるし
Do we have a map of Ezo?
エゾの地図ってあるの？
This is the only detailed one we've got.
一番詳しいのでコレしかない
We won't know the landscape until we get there...
実際の地形は　行ってみないと分からないから
...so we have no choice but to
measure the altitude once we're over land.
上陸後は高度を取るしかないよ
But as long as we're over land, Union radars won't spot us, right?
でも上陸さえしちゃえば
ユニオンのレーダーには　つかまらないんじやないか？
The Velaciela's radar profile should be smaller than a bird.
ヴェラシーラの返す影は　 小鳥より小さいハズだろ
Yeah.
たぶんなよほど運がなければ…
Unless we're really unlucky.
Sawatari!
沢渡！
Hold on!
待ってて！
It's all right.
だ大丈夫だよそんなに高くないから…
It's not that high.
We've done this before...
私たち前にも…
I'm glad I made it in time.
よかった間に合って…今
I'll just...
わっ！
Are you all right?
大丈夫か？
Yeah.
うん
Sorry.
ごめんね
Thank you.
ありがとう
H-Hey!
ハハハ！
He wasn't expecting that!
驚いたぜ！
何すんだよ！
What did you do that for?!
ワッ！
よせよヒロキ！
Stop it, Hiroki!
ハハハごめんツイさ
Sorry.
I just had to.
What did you say?!
何だと！？
What the heck are you thinking, anyway?
お前は一体何がしたいんだよ！？
C'mon, don't be so angry.
そんなに怒るなよ
I'm angry all right!
怒るぜ！お前はもう上がってくるな！
Just stay there!
Let's go, Sawatari.
行こうぜ沢渡
Takuya...
タクヤぁ……
Sawatari, say something to him!
沢渡何か言ってやってよ
ふふ…ごめんねタクヤ君
Sorry, Takuya-kun.
Hiroki's stupid.
ヒロキがバカなんだよ
Forget about him and let's just go.
いいから行こうぜ
Hey, Takuya...
おいタクヤ…
Earlier, for just a second, I was having a dream.
わたしね
さっき一瞬だけ夢見てたんだ
A dream?
夢？どんな夢？
What kind of dream?
んー…
あぁ　忘れちゃったなぁでもたぶん　あの塔の夢
I forgot.
But it was probably about that Tower.
It's an unbelievable view, isn't it?
ウソみたいな眺めだもんなユニオンはすごいよ
The Union is incredible.
The tip of the Tower looks like it might even lead to some other world.
塔の先ー
他の世界まで　つながっていそうだ
あぁ…
The sun...
夕陽ー
It's setting so slowly, isn't it?
なかなか沈まないね…
That summer was truly special...
ほんとうにあれは特別な夏だった
But from that point on,
the world around me would betray me many times over.
でも僕を囲む世界はこの先　何度でも僕を裏切る
It's been three years since that day... since I last saw Sawatari.
あれから3年あの日を最後に
僕は沢渡には会っていない
Three Years Later
Union Territory, Ezo Airspace
Fall of the Same Year, in Aomori City
Wartime Special Information Processing Research Lab, Aomori Army College, Commissioned by the US NSA
Pay no mind to our visitors, all right?
お客さまが来たけど　気にせずにね
First phase completed.
ファーストフェイズ終了 次行こう
Proceed to the next phase.
Okay!
はい
Next is the filtering stage.
次　濾過ステージ
Commencing second phase.
セカンドフェイズ開始します
Directional resolution is 25% higher than before.
指向性解像度前回より25％プラスです
That's good.
いいね今度こそ行けるかな
I wonder if we can do it this time?
Choose a good algorithm, okay?
アルゴリズムうまく選んでいけよ
Yes, sir.
はい
How's that algorithm, Shirakawa?
白川アルゴリズムは？
I modified the filtering for group sampling.
グループ抽出フィルタリングに手を加えました
This idea's based on Ekusun Tsukinoe's thesis.
エクスン・ツキノエの論文がもとです
Ekusun Tsukinoe?
エクスン・ツキノエって
From the Union?
ユニオンのか？
Yes.
はい
What?
何？どうやってそんなコトを
How did you...
Just a moment, please.
待って下さい反応しだいに増強…
Reaction is starting to increase.
Who's that?
誰なんですか？
The Union researcher who first proved the existence of parallel worlds.
初めて平行世界の実存を証明したユニオンの研究者だよ
They say he designed the Tower.
塔の設計者だって言われてる
I have it!
捉えた！
Exposure reactions confirmed in orientations XA, YC and ZC.
XAYCZC方向に露出反応確認
There are five...
分岐宇宙5いや6あります！
No... Six branch universes!
Six?
6つか！同調ステージ開始
Begin harmonization stage.
Get us a link, all right?
つながってくれよ！
Commencing third phase.
サードフェイズ開始します
Each of you try connecting with the closest parallel world.
最も近い平行宇宙にそれぞれ接続アプローチ開始
Begin your approach.
Yes, sir!
はい
He's fast!
…速い！
Shirakawa-kun is the closest.
白川君が一番近い接続可能領域まであと12エクサ
Twelve more Exa to reach the connectable territory.
11...
11　10　9.4　9.2…
10...
9.4...
9.2...
We have a connection!
つながりました！
We've successfully connected to a nearby branch universe.
近接する一つの分岐宇宙に接続成功
The exposure reactions are stable.
露出反応安定してます
Good.
よしこのまま変換ステージに移ろう
Let's move on to the conversion stage.
Commencing fourth phase, spatial displacement with the parallel world.
フォースフェイズ
平行世界との空間置換開始します
Disparate matter conversion confirmed. Radius is 60 nanos.
半径60ナノ空間の異相変換確認！急速に拡大
It's expanding rapidly.
We'll soon be able to confirm visually.
間もなく肉眼で確認できます
This isn't good.
ダメだ
It's no good!
ダメです！
Exposure reactions are decreasing.
露出反応減退
We can't maintain the connection with the parallel world any longer.
平行世界との接続をこれ以上維持できません！
Wave function has converged.
波動関数収れん分岐宇宙完全に消失
The branch universes have completely disappeared.
We succeeded in replacing
approximately a 1.3 mm radius of disparate matter.
半径約1.3ミリの異相置換に成功しました
Good work.
お疲れさまでした！
Thanks.
お疲れさま！
Professor Tomizawa, is Shirakawa-kun free now?
冨澤先生白川君空きました？
He is.
空いたよ何だ君らいつも一緒だなぁ
I swear, you two are always together.
You were the one who asked me to stay
close to him until he gets used to this place.
先生が慣れるまでついててやれって
言ったんじゃないですか
I said that?
そうだっけ？
By the way, Maki-chan...
あ　マキちやん　僕　明日から東京出張だからね
I'm going to Tokyo tomorrow on business.
That meeting to discuss our research findings, right?
研究報告会でしたよね？
That too, but it seems they found the key.
それもあるけど　例の鍵が見つかったみたいなんだ
The key?
鍵って…前先生がおっしやってた？
You mean the one you told me about before?
Yeah.
うん
Things could get busy for you and the rest of the Brain Science team.
きみら脳科学チームは忙しくなるかもね
あっ
Maki-san...
マキさん…
There've been a lot of military officers here recently, huh?
…軍人さん最近よく来るね
The one in the suit is probably with the NSA.
スーツのほうたぶんNSAですよ
NSA?
NSA？
The National Security Agency.
国家安全保障局
Oh...
ふうん…テロの噂最近多いもんね
Well, there have been a lot of rumors about terrorism lately.
Did it go well today?
今日はうまくいったの？
Still not well enough.
まだまだです
We've just barely managed to replace
enough matter to see with the naked eye.
ぎりぎり肉眼で見える程度の置き換えがやっとで
We're a long way from the Union's Tower.
ユニオンの塔には及びもつきません
Well, that can't be helped.
それは仕方ないわよ
They had a big head start on us, right from basic physics.
もともと基礎物理から大きくリードされちゃってるんだし
I saw that Ezo aerial photo too.
エゾのあの航空写真私も見たよ
What we don't know is why the disparate
matter conversion stops at a 2 km radius from the Tower.
分からないのは
異相変換がなぜ塔の周囲2キロで止まっているかです
If the Tower was built to be used as a weapon, it doesn't make sense.
攻撃目的だとしたらそれじや意味がないし…
Maybe an accident or something knocked it out of commission...
何かの事故で機能が停止しているのか
Or maybe it's nothing more than a simple experimental facility.
それとも単にそれだけの実験施設なのかしら
Either that, or the matter conversion is
something the designer didn't even intend.
あるいは異相変換自体が
設計者も意図しなかった機能の暴走なのか…
Professor Tomizawa says there may be some external factor...
富澤教授は
塔の機能を抑え込んでいるようなー
...keeping the Tower from functioning properly.
何らかの外因があるんじゃないかって言ってますね
Say, Shirakawa-kun...
ね白川君明日は何してるの？
What are you doing tomorrow?
High school's on break, too, right?
高校もお休みだよね？
I kinda need to do some research.
ちょっと調べたいことがあるので…
At the library?
図書館？
No.
イエ知り合いの工場に
At a factory that someone I know runs...
Someone wants to see the factory?
見たいってうちは見学施設じゃねえんだぞ
We don't offer tours, y'know!
Huh?
え？何？
What was that?
A girl?
女の子？いくつの子？
How old is she?
How should I know?
知りませんよ！
But I'd say she's pretty... probably.
でもまあ綺麗なヒトですよ たぶん
Well, okay!
ああじゃあ待ってるからねー
I'll be waiting.
Wow!
へえー
What amazing antennas!
すごいアンテナですねー！
ハハハ
Well, some of them are a little illegal...
ちょっとだけ非合法なのも交じってるんですけどね
...but they can pick up signals from some pretty interesting places.
これで結構面白いトコにもつながるんですよ
Wow.
へェー…
So, you specialize in brain research, Maki-san?
じゃあ　マキさんは脳の研究が専門なんですか？
Yes.
ハイ　記憶とか睡眠とか夢とか…
Things like memories, sleep and dreams.
But you and Takuya work at the same lab?
タクヤと一緒の研究室ですよね？
I thought you were studying the Tower.
お前塔の研究やってるんじやなかったっけ？
I am...
ええ　俺のほうは塔の研究で…どう言えばいいのかな
I do research on the Tower and...
How can I put this?
Both of our research deals with parallel worlds.
どちらも平行世界を扱う研究なんです
Parallel worlds?
平行世界？
You know how a person will have dreams at night?
あの…ヒトが夜夢を見るみたいに
Well, the universe has "dreams," too.
この宇宙も夢を見ているんです
Our world hides all these different possibilities, things that could have been, inside dreams.
“こうであったかもしれない”っていう様々な可能性を
この世界は夢の中に隠していて
We call these "parallel worlds" or "branch universes."
そのことを私たちは
平行世界とか分岐宇宙って呼んでいます
My research involves studying the effects that
these parallel worlds have on people's brains and dreams.
私の研究はその平行世界が
人の脳や夢に及ぼす影響を調べることです
A popular theory states that the Union Tower is observing these same things.
ユニオンのあの塔も
同じものを観測してるって説が有力なんです
Technology has allowed us to view the parallel worlds...
テクノロジーで平行世界が　観測できるようになった一方で
...but the nervous systems of various life forms
may have subconsciously sensed them for millennia.
生物の脳も太古から無意識のうち
こそれを感知してきたのかもしれない
What we call "precognition" or "premonitions"
may actually be a kind of exchange of information...
量子レベルで脳の中を行き来する分岐宇宙の情報が
...about the branch universes that
occurs at the quantum level within the brain.
ひょっとしたら
ヒトの予感や予知といったものの源泉なのかもしれない
That's the kind of research that I do.
そんな研究をしています
Wow.
…へェ
The dreams of the universe... Sounds romantic, huh?
宇宙の見る夢なんて　なんかロマンチックですねえ
"Romantic"?
ロマンチック…
Got a problem with that?
何だよ
No...
イエ…
別に…
I think you're amazing, Maki-san.
でもマキさんはご立派です
Imagine, being a researcher at a facility that does
consultation work for the government at such a young age!
お若くして政府諮問機関の研究員とは！
Please, it's nothing special.
イエそんな…でも私塔に憧れてたから
The Tower fascinates me.
It's fulfilling work.
やりがいはあるんです
To tell the truth, it used to fascinate me, too.
俺もですよ実は憧れたなァ
Anyway, the one who's really amazing here is Shirakawa-kun!
でも本当にすごいのは　白川君のほうなんです！
He's not just the youngest outside researcher we have,
he's the most enthusiastic one!
最年少の外部研究員でイチバン熱心で！
Right from the start, I thought he was really cool!
私　前からカッコイイなーって
What?
イヤそんな
No...
I'm not like that at all.
俺なんて…全然…
I'd better be going now.
私そろそろおいとましないと
Oh, I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
It looks like I ate most of them.
何だか私　殆ど自分で　食べちゃったみたいで
Don't worry about it.
イエイエ…
Takuya, you going to the city?
タクヤ市内まで行くのか？
Yes.
ええマキさんを送って
I'm taking Maki-san home.
Give me a ride too.
俺も乗せてってよ
Huh?
エーッ！
Okay.
いいですよ
What?!
エーッ！
Can you drop me off at the station?
駅で降ろしてくれるか
Aren't you going home?
岡部さん帰らないんですか？
No, I'm going to Tokyo tomorrow on business.
明日から仕事で東京なんだよ
Okabe-san...
岡部さん
Huh?
ん？
Have you thought about that favor I asked?
お願いしてたこと考えてくれました？
What was it again?
何だっけ？
Uilta.
ウィルタのことですよ
Ah.
ああ…オマエもクドイな
Persistent, aren't you?
Anyway, it looks like the lab is keeping you pretty busy.
それより研究室頑張ってるみたいじゃないか
And the work is good, right?
そっちがやりがいがあるんだろ？
That's not really the point.
そういうわけじゃ…
I just want to settle this Tower business... and soon.
ただ早く片付けちゃいたいんです
あの塔のことは
September, Tokyo
What's the matter?
どうしました？
Well, I didn't think you could see the Tower from Tokyo, too.
ああ…いえ
東京からも　あの塔が見えるとは思わなかったもので
Well, there are days like that sometimes.
ああ　時々そういう日があります　今日は空気が澄んでますから
But the air's quite clear today.
This way, please.
…こちらです
That's the progression of her condition
since she was admitted to this hospital.
そちらが　この病院にいらしてからの経過です
She began showing symptoms in the summer of her eighth grade.
中学3年の夏に発症原因は不明
Cause: Unknown.
Her sleep cycles gradually grew longer and in just the first two months...
次第に睡眠時間が長くなり
覚醒状態が一定時間維持できたのは
...she was only able to stay awake for limited periods of time.
最初の2ヶ月のみ
She's been sound asleep for the past three years.
この3年間眠り続けている…と
So, she's been having some sort of dream?
何らかの夢を見続けているわけですね？
That's what the brain waves we've recorded would indicate.
そういう脳波は記録されています
ふうん…DNA鑑定は？
And what about the DNA test?
On page six.
6枚目です
I see.
…なるほどね…分断された血筋なわけだ
Her family's separated, eh?
Fine.
結構
These are the documents requested
from the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.
ではこちらが厚生労働省からの要請書です
Note: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare
Prognosis on Subject A (August 1996-September 1999)
1996-Type Varietal Narcolepsy Patient Transfer Request
You'll receive the official documents
as soon as the transfer date is decided.
移送の日にちが決まり次第正式な書類が届きます
What's this letter?
この手紙は？
Something the patient was writing at
the start of her hospitalization, it seems.
患者さんが入院当初書いていたもののようです
Have you read it?
読みました？
No.
イエ
Note: Okabe-san c/o Emishi Plant
N5-32-8 Ookawadai, Tsugaru County, Aomori Prefecture
Emishi Manufacturing...
エミシ製作所？
Note: Japan-US Military Affairs Research Report Meeting
Thus, by analyzing the deviations between the multiple universes...
このように行く手で枝分かれしていくー
多元宇宙の偏りを検知することで
...it becomes possible to render
a highly accurate prediction of our own future.
非常に高精度の未来予測が可能になります
Herein lies the ultimate goal of my own research laboratory.
私の研究室の最終的な目標もここです
This is not a conventional theoretical model or probability theory.
これは従来の理論モデルや確率論ではなく
This is information based entirely on the results of an actual future.
あくまでも現実の未来の結果をもとにした情報であり
The influence it could have on decision-making in
the political and military arenas will likely be incalculable.
このことが政治・軍事の意思決定の場面に及ぼす影響は
計り知れないでしょう
However, to be perfectly candid...
ただ率直に言って
...we must also consider that the Union...
一方でユニオン側の量子重力論の応用技術は
...has already applied quantum gravity
theory to technology far superior to our own.
我々とは比較にならないほど高いレベルに達していると
考えざるを得ません
Construction of the symbolic
Ezo Tower is thought to have started in 1974...
エゾに建つ　あのシンボリックな塔の建設が始まったのは
...immediately after the North-South Separation.
南北分断直後の74年
Its operation started in 1996 or so.
稼動が開始されたのは96年頃と推測されていますが
It is ironic to us, in the Alliance that Ekusun Tsukinoe...
設計の中心的役割を果たしたと言われているー
エクスン・ツキノエが
...said to have played a central role in
its design is originally from the mainland.
もともとは本州の出身であることは
我々連合側にとっては皮肉なことです
Next, I'll explain some of the technological innovations...
さて
続いて実際に平行世界の情報を検地していくための
...we've already used to glean information on the parallel worlds.
いくつかの新しい技術的試みについて説明します…
When I saw you I thought, "Now, there's a guy with a bad attitude."
態度の悪いヤツがいるなと思ったよ
Hey, I was listening.
ちゃんと話は聞いてたぜ 要するにアレだろ
Basically, you wanna have a peek at
God's dreams and do a little analyzing, right?
神サマの見ている夢を覗き見て夢判断をしたいってことだろ
Well, that's more or less correct.
まあ大体合ってる何だ岡ちゃん興味あるの？
What's this, Oka-chan?
You find this interesting?
I've done my homework.
ちょっと予習したんだよ
Anyway, what do you say we do something tonight?
それより今晩久しぶりにどうだ？
It's been a while.
Shirakawa-kun's excellent.
白川君は優秀だよ確かにイイ素質がある
He's definitely got talent.
You're glad you talked to him, right?
声かけてみてよかっただろう
Yeah.
うんでも岡ちやん
But tell me, Oka-chan...
Just when did you start helping students find jobs?
いつから学生の斡旋なんて始めたの？
Well, these two are a little special.
いや…
あいつらはちょっと…特別なんだ
These two?
あいつら？
Yeah.
ああ
There's another one who should be in Tokyo by now...
もう一人心配なのが東京に来てるはずなんだが
...but I can't get hold of him. I'm a little worried.
運絡が取れねぇんだよな…奴ら二人で飛行機作ってたんだぜ
Y'know, those two were building their own airplane.
Hey, that brings back memories!
そりゃ懐かしいね…
Wait. You came to Tokyo for that?
何だいそのための上京？もっと違う用事かと思ったよ
I thought you were here for something completely different.
Like what?
何だと思った？
Uilta.
ウィルクの件
Actually, you're right.
実はそうだそっちが本題
That's the main reason.
We're going to get our hands on a PL outer-shell bomb.
PL外殻爆弾が手に入ることになった
Don't ask from where.
入手経路は聞くなよ
I don't have to.
聞かなくても大体分かるよ
I already more or less have an idea.
So, what are you getting at?
で何？
Don't tell me you're asking if it will work against the Tower?
…まさか塔に効くかどうかってこと？
Bingo.
…そうだ
I'm sure it will.
そりゃあ効くんじゃない？
The exterior of the Tower will likely vaporize instantly.
塔の外装は一瞬で蒸発するだろうし…
The interior is supposedly made up of huge nanonet ribbons...
内部はナノネットの巨大なリボンで
構成されてるらしいんだが
...but it will probably go down in flames too.
これもたぶん燃え落ちるだろうな…
Yeah.
そうだねPL外殼弾は最適かもしれない
A PL outer-shell bomb may be the best suited for the job.
I see.
そうか
You know...
でもさ
You might want to reconsider.
ウィルタのそういう行動は開戦の機運を高めるよ
If Uilta does this, it will increase the chances of starting a war.
やめとけば？
That's why we're doing it.
だからやるんだ
It's already been decided on?
決定事項なの？
More or less.
大体な
A lot of powerful people are eager for war.
開戦を望んでるエライ人たちがいっぱいいるからな
I thought Uilta's philosophy was reunification with the North.
きみらの理念は南北統一じゃなかったのかい？
Still is.
今でもそうだぜ
It just feels like destroying the Tower would be such a waste.
もったいない気はするけどなあ…
From the Alliance standpoint,
it's the product of unbelievable technologies.
あれは連合側からは信じられないようなー
技術の結晶だぜ
Besides, it's just standing there. Its impact on us is negligible...
どうせただ建ってるだけで現実的な影響はないんだし
Don't be coy with me.
隠すなよ今は止まっているように見えるが
The Tower appears to currently be out of commission...
...but it's possible that it's an extremely powerful weapon,
one that can turn the space around it inside-out.
塔は周囲の空間を裏返すー
強力な兵器である可能性がある
You knew about that?
知ってたのか
Yeah.
ああ
It sure makes for a beautiful view, though...
僕はあの眺め好きなんだけどなぁ…
Every once in a while,
there's bound to be a romantic who thinks like you.
時々そういうロマンチックなヤツが
いるよなあ
Can I ask you a question, Oka-chan?
…岡ちゃんさぁ僕も聞いていいかな
ん？
Not too long ago...
少し前に　あの塔の秘密につながりそうな人間が
...they found someone who might be
connected to the secrets of the Tower.
見つかったんだ
Is that so?
へえ
A girl, still in her teens.
まだ十代の女の子だよ
I see.
へえ…それで？
And?
You know her, don't you?
…岡ちゃんの知ってる子じゃないのか？
I'm not trying to pester you...
しつこいかもしれないけど
...but it'd be better to keep this from
Shirakawa-kun until we know more about her...
彼女のことハッキリするまで白川君には
内緒にしといたほうがいい
...especially if they were close.
仲がよかったのならなおさらだ
He'll find out eventually.
いずれバレるぜ
Even so, we don't have to worry him about it now, right?
だとしても　今から悩ませる必要はないだろう
And anyway, this has already fallen under the NSA's jurisdiction.
もう安全保障局の管轄なんだ　クビを突っ込まないほうがいい
It'd be best if you stayed out of it.
What kind of dreams does the universe have?
この宇宙が見る夢が　どんなものなのか
I'd like to have them, too.
僕もそれは見たいと思うけどね
A cold, deep wind blew there,
a wind that seemed as if it had come from a distant universe.
そこは　ずっと遠くの宇宙からやってきたようなー
冷たく深い風が吹いていて
Even the air had the smell of a different universe.
空気には　違う宇宙の匂いがしました
The sky...
…空と雲と崩れた街
The clouds...
A city in ruins...
There are no people, no matter how far I walk.
どこまで歩いても誰もいない
I'm cold...
寒い…
What am I doing in a place like this?
私どうしてこんなところにいるの？
Someone...
誰か
Please, someone!
ねえ誰か…
Hiroki-kun...
ヒロキ君…
That dream again...
またあの夢だ
We ended up not flying the Velaciela, after all.
ヴェラシーラを　結局　僕たちは飛ばさなかった
It was kind of a shock when Sayuri
disappeared without saying anything three years ago.
3年前ー
サユリが僕たちに何も言わないで
消えてしまったことは　それなりにショックだったし
Because of that, we stopped working on the plane...
そのことで飛行機作りをやめてしまった自分たち自身にも
...and I think that in turn made us angry at ourselves.
僕たちは　腹を立てていたのだと思う
After graduating from middle school...
申学卒業後　タクヤは青森県内の高挾に進学し
...Takuya entered a high school in Aomori Prefecture...
...and I entered one here in Tokyo.
僕は東京の高校に来た
From here, I thought, I wouldn't have to look at the Tower anymore.
東京まで来れば　ユニオンの塔は見えなくなると
思ったからだ
But I was in for a disappointment.
でもそれは期待はずれで
Sometimes, when the weather was nice, I could still see it in the distance...
時々　天気がいいと　東京からも塔はかすかに見えた
...and I'd be overwhelmed by a depression that would last all day.
そういう日　僕は一日暗い気持ちに支配された
この戦車　藤沢君のふるさとまで行くんだよね？
These tanks are going all the way to your hometown, right?
Yeah, I guess.
ああ　そうだな
Hey.
ね
This looks slow enough to jump on, don't you think?
こういうのって　ゆっくりで飛び乗れそうじゃない？
What do you say we hop a ride to Aomori together?
青森まで二人で密航しようか？
Sometimes Okabe-san would send me letters, letting me know how things were going.
時と岡部さんからは　近況を知らせる手紙が届いた
I've never once written him back.
返事は一度も出していない
Every time I get to my room and shut the door...
部屋にたどり着いて　ドアを閉めるたび
...I feel a stabbing pain in my heart as if all
the bones in my body are breaking through my skin.
まるで体中の骨が皮震を突き破るようなー
激しい心の痛みを感じる
And I wonder when it was that
I became burdened with something like this.
いつの間に
僕はこんなものを抱え込んでしまったのだろう
And now, the latest news on the highly tense international relations.
次に緊張の高まる国際関係のニュースです
Note: To Fujisawa Hiroki-san
At the UN Security Council held on the 19th...
19日に行われた国連安全保障理事会で
...America once again demanded that the Union
should allow a UN inspection group into its Ezo Tower facility.
アメリカはユニオンに対しエゾにある塔施設への
国連査察団受け入れを再度要求しましたし
In response to this...
I was living alone, and the nights felt long.
これに対し　ユニオン政府は
一人暮らしの夜は長く感じた
...the Union Government stubbornly maintained their staunch refusal...
断固拒否の強硬姿勢を改めて示し…
When I couldn't find anything to occupy my time...
うまく時間をやり過ごせないときは
...I would walk to the nearby station
and pretend I was waiting for someone.
僕は近くの駅まで歩き
誰かを待っているフリをしながら時悶を潰して
When I got tired of that...
それにも飽きると
...I walked back to my room as slowly as possible.
部屋までの帰り道をなるべくゆっくりと歩いた
I had friends at high school...
高校に友達はいたけれど
...but I found that other than when I was wearing the uniform...
制服を着ているとき以外は
...I really didn't want to be around them.
どうしてかあまり一緒にいたいと思えなかった
Come to think of it, in a city of more than thirty million people...
3000万以上の人間が暮らす街で
考えてみれば会いたい人も話したい人も
...there wasn't a single person I wanted to see or talk to.
僕には誰もいなかった
Sometimes, on days like those, I would dream of Sayuri.
そういう日々の中で　 時々サユリの夢を見た
I'd dream that she was in some cold place all by herself.
それは　どこか冷たい場所に一人きりでいるサユリを
I would look for her, frantically...
必死に探す夢で
But in the end, I never find her.
結局いつも　サユリの姿は見つからなかった
However, even after I awoke...
ただー
心をふるわすようなサユリの気配だけは
...I could feel Sayuri's presence lingering inside me...
目が覚めてからも体に残っていた
...and it would make my heart tremble.
One day, I realized it was my third winter since I'd come to Tokyo.
気が付けば
東京に来てから3度目の冬だ
It was as if I was holding my breath underwater... Cold, deep water.
まるでー
深く冷たい水の中で息を止め続けているようなー
And it was like that every day.
そんな毎日だった
I'm the only one...
僕だけが
I'm the only one left in the whole world...
私だけが
世界に一人きりとりのこされている
That's how it feels.
そんな気がずる
March, The Following Year
Off Cape Shirakami, Southern Tip of Union Territory
It was my dream to come to Ezo someday.
俺ー
いつかエゾに来るのが夢だったんですよ
Now, here I am, easy as that.
あっけなく来れちゃうもんですね
It's just the southern tip, though.
ここはほんの南端だけどな
You have family on the Union side or something?
ユニオン側に家族でもいるのか？
No, it's nothing like that.
そういうわけじゃないんですが
Your generation was born after the Separation.
お前は分断後の世代だからな…
So, I can understand your fascination with it all...
憧れる気持ちも分からなくはないよ
But the boss got taken away from his family because of the Separation.
社長なんかは南北分断で家族と別れてるからな
So, I'll bet he feels differently about the issue.
また別の気持ちがあると思うぜ
Really?
えそうなんですか？
Still, I didn't expect this.
でも意外だったよ
Huh?
え？
I didn't think that the boss would involve you in this.
社長がお前を巻き込むとは思わなかった
I begged and pleaded.
俺が無理やり頼み込んだんです
And I said that if he didn't bring me along,
I'd file a report with the Public Safety Commission.
連れてってくれなきゃ　公安にタレ込むって言って
What a dangerous thing you said.
オマエ危ないことを…
Boss!
社長！
This is not funny!
冗談じゃねえぞ
What a stupid official!
まったく　マヌケな役人だぜ内通がバレたんだ
They found out about our communication!
Ship us out!
出してくれ
That was a little too close this time.
今回はちょっと　危なかったですね
Yeah, but now, we're that much closer to infiltrating their airspace.
まあお陰で　侵空のめどがついたぜ
I guess it was a good thing we came all the way out here.
ここまで来たかいがあったってもんだ
なぁ
Boss, there's a ship!
社長船がいます
It's a patrol boat!
巡視船です！
貴船は我が国の領海を侵犯している
直ちに停船せよさもなければ銃撃する
It's already decided that we're goin' to war anyway...
どうせ開戦は決定済みだってのに
What're they taking their jobs so seriously for?!
真面目に働きやがって
繰り返す
This is not good.
マズイな振り切ってくれ
Lose them!
Yes, sir!
ハイ
Three more minutes 'til the border!
国境まであと3分だ佐藤宮川銃座に出てくれ
Sato! Miyagawa!
Get to the gun emplacement!
直ちに停泊せよさもなければ銃撃する
Takuya!
タクヤ！
Are you all right, Takuya?!
大丈夫か？タクヤ！！
Those wings...
…あの翼
I know them!
わたし知ってる！
When I wake up...
目を覚まし　一瞬
...for a second I don't quite know where I am.
自分がどこにいるのか　よく分からなくなる
Sometimes, I think that maybe I came to the wrong place.
僕は
もしかして間違えた場所に来てしまったのではないかと
時々思う
By now, I feel the dream about Sayuri is more real than reality itself.
今ではサユリの夢のほうを
現実よりも現実らしく感じている
She's in a hospital?
入院先？
Note: Okabe-san c/o Emishi Plant 5-32-8 Ookawadai,
Tsugaru County, Aomori Prefecture
Note: Sawatari Sayuri
Sayuri...
サユリ…
Hiroki-kun... Takuya-kun...
“ヒロキ君タクヤ君”
I'm sorry for leaving without saying anything.
“二人の前から黙っていなくなってしまったこと”
“ごめんなさい”
It makes me sad... I wanted to spend the summer with you.
“夏休みを一緒に過ごしたかったのに残念です”
When I woke up, I was in a hospital in Tokyo...
“目が覚めたとき私は東京の病院にいて”
...and I've been here ever since.
“それからすっと入院しています”
The people here tell me I should sever all the ties I had from before...
“病院の人には今までの関係は一切断ち切るべきだからと”
“言われていたのですが”
...but I begged them, and so now I'm writing you this letter.
“どうしてもとお願いして今これを書いています”
I'll send this to Okabe-ojisan, so the two of you will read it.
“二人に読んでもらえるように”
“岡部のおじさん宛てに送ります”
But I don't quite know what I should write.
“でも何を書いたらいいのかよく分かりません”
I've been having the same dream, over and over.
“何度も同じ夢を見ます”
A dream where I'm all alone in an empty universe.
“誰もいない　がらんどうの宇宙に私一人だけがいる夢”
I'm so alone that my fingers, cheeks...
“その夢の中では　私の全部ー”
“指や頬ー”
...fingernails, heels and even the ends of my hair...
“爪やかかとや”
“髪の毛の先までが”
Everything aches from the loneliness.
“寂しさに強く痛がっています”
The times we spent together in a world filled with warmth...
“3人で過ごした　あのぬくもりに満ちた世界”
...seem more like a dream to me now than my dream.
“あの頃のほうが　まるで夢だったみたいです”
But so long as I don't lose the memories of those days...
“…でも　あの頃の思い出さえなくさなければ”
“もしかして私はこの先”
...I think that, even if just a little, I can stay connected to reality.
“ほんのかすかでも”
“現実につながっていられるかもしれないって”
“そう思っています”
She was transferred?
転院したんですか？
Yes, about a week ago.
はい1週間ほど前に
The hospital she was transferred to,
would be able to tell you more, if you'd care to ask them.
詳しくは移送先の病院に聞いていただけますか
Okay.
はい…
Oh, which room was she in?
あの…沢渡さんの入っていた病室って
Hiroki-kun... Takuya-kun...
“ヒロキ君タクヤ君”
Did that beautiful white airplane of
yours make it to the Tower beyond the sea?
“あの白い綺麗な飛行機は”
“海のむこうのあの塔まで無事に飛びましたか？”
What is this?
何だろう？
It feels like my dream...
夢と同じ空気だ…
Sawatari...
…沢渡
Are you there?
…そこにいるのか？
All this time... All this time...
…ずっと
I've been looking for you!
探してた…！
Sawatari...
…沢渡
I really want to keep my promise this time.
俺　今度こそ　約束を叶えたいんだ
I'm going to fly you to the Tower in the Velaciela.
沢渡を塔まで乗せて　ヴェラシーラを飛ばすよ
I feel if I do that, we'll meet again.
そうすれば僕たちはまた会えるっていう気がするんだ
I won't leave you alone.
ねえ
もう一人にはしないよ僕はもう何も諦めない
And I won't give up anymore, on anything.
I'll protect you forever.
ずっと沢渡を守るよ約束する
I promise.
Yes.
うん…約束…
It's a promise.
Let's fly to the Tower... together.
一緒に塔まで飛ぼう
ん？
Professor!
先生来て下さい
Please come over here!
Operational levels at the Tower have suddenly increased!
塔の稼動レベルが急に上昇したんです
The range of the disparate matter conversion is also expanding rapidly!
異相変換の範囲が急激に広がっていっています！
Conscious activity in the subject is increasing at the same rate!
同じタイミングで
対象の意識活動レベルも上昇してるんです
This could be an indicator that she's waking up.
目が覚める前兆かもしれません
Does this mean...
これってやっぱり
Disparate matter conversion is now in excess of a 20 km radius.
異相変換の半径20キロを超えました！
Does it...
これは…
Does it plan on overwriting the entire world?
世界を書き換えるつもりなのか？
Conscious activity in the subject is decreasing!
対象の意識レベルが低下に転じました！
Disparate matter conversion is also slowing down...
異相変換のスピードも低下
It's going to stop.
停止します…！
An area of approximately a 26 km radius
has been overwritten with a parallel world.
半径約26キロまでの範囲が平行宇宙と書き換わりました
Conscious activity in the subject has returned to normal.
対象の意識レベルも通常の水準まで落ちています
The subject's sleep is stabilizing again.
睡眠再び安定しつつあります
Professor Tomizawa...
富澤先生…
Yeah.
うん…
As we thought, it's the subject's sleep that
has been keeping the Tower's activity in check.
やはり対象の眠りが塔の活動を抑えていた鍵だったんだ
For now, information that the Tower acquires from the parallel worlds...
塔の捉える平行宇宙の情報は
...is being discharged into the subject's
dreams rather than eroding the surrounding space.
周囲の空間を浸食するかわりに
今は対象の夢に流れ込んでいる
We have no choice but to ensure that Sawatari Sayuri keeps dreaming.
沢渡サユリには
夢を見続けていてもらうしかない
It might have just been a dream...
ただ　夢を見ていたのかもしれない
But even so, the places where Sayuri brushed my skin remained warm.
それでも肌に触れたサユリのぬくもりは
僕の体を温め続けていた
On that distant day...
今はもう遠いあの日ー
...we made a promise that we couldn't keep.
僕たちは叶えられない約束をした
Hey, Takuya-kun...
……ねえタクヤ君
This may sound strange, but promise that you won't laugh?
おかしな話かもしれないけど笑わない？
Note: Train Arriving
What is it?
えなに？笑わないよ
I won't laugh.
Okay, I'll tell you.
じゃあ話すねあのね……
Listen...
It's about a dream I've been having a lot lately.
最近よく見る　夢の話
A tall tower?
高い塔？ユニオンの塔みたいな？
You mean, like the Union Tower?
No.
ううん　もっといびつで…不思議な形
It's more crooked.
It has a really strange shape.
I'm inside it, but there's a bunch of others just like it all around.
私のいる塔の他にも
そういうのが周りにはいっぱい建ってて
For some reason, I know that each one is a different world...
私にはなぜか分かるんだけど
その一つ一つが別々の世界　この宇宙の見ている夢なの
A dream that this universe is having.
I haven't been able to leave that place for a long time.
私はずっとその場所から出ることができなくて
I've been all by myself, and very, very lonely.
ずっと一人きりですごく寂しくて…
And then...
それでね
Just when I feel like I'm going to lose myself...
もうきっと心はこのままー
消えちゃうんだろうなっていう時にね
...I see a white airplane in the sky.
空に白い飛行機が見えるの
A white airplane?
白い飛行機？
Yeah.
うん
And then?
それから？
That's the end of the dream.
夢はそこでおしまい
Civilian Hospital, Tsugaru County, Aomori Prefecture
Thank goodness!
よかった！
Shirakawa-kun, you're awake.
白川君目が覚めたのね
Maki-san...
マキさん…
I was really worried.
心配したんだから
Um... Why?
あのどうして
Does your shoulder still hurt?
まだ肩は痛む？
No.
イエ…
Pardon me.
ちょっとゴメンね
It looks like your fever's come down, too.
熱も下がったみたい
Say, are you hungry?
ねお腹空いてない？何か食べる？
Do you want something to eat?
I've got apples and bananas.
りんごとバナナとあとケーキも買ってきちゃった
I even went and bought some cakes.
What would you like?
どれがいいかな…
A Few Days Later
Special Hospital Ward, Aomori Army College
You can't get in there with that ID card, Shirakawa-kun.
白川君のlDじゃ入れないよ
How's that shoulder? Better?
怪我はもういいの？
Yes.
あはいすみませんご心配おかけして…
Sorry for making you worry.
Um...
あの…
So, Maki-chan told you, eh?
マキちゃんから聞いたんだって？
You want to see her?
会っていくかい？
They say she stays asleep...
眠り続けるのは塔から流れ込む平行世界の情報に
...because the Tower is feeding her information
from the parallel worlds and her mind can't cope.
彼女の脳が耐えられないからだと推測されている
Personally, I think if her sleep is broken...
もし彼女の眠りが破られれば
...the parallel worlds will swallow up this one in the blink of an eye...
塔を中心に世界は瞬く間に
平行宇宙に飲み込まれることになると思うよ
...starting with that Tower.
Still, we don't even know how we could wake her up.
もっとも
どうしたら彼女を目覚めさせることができるのかも
我々には分からないんだけどね
With the war about to begin...
開戦を控えて数日中に
...they've decided to transfer her to
NSA headquarters in a couple of days.
本国のNSA本部へ移送されることが決まったよ
The Alliance has really fallen behind in this field...
この分野で大きく立ち後れている連合にとっては
So, this girl's a valuable sample.
彼女は貴重なサンプルなんだ
Why did it have to be Sawatari?
…どうして沢渡なんでしょうか？
There's a lot more we don't know than we do...
分かっていないことのほうが多いが
...but it's probably no coincidence.
たぶん偶然ではないと僕は思う
Ekusun Tsukinoe, the designer of the Tower...
塔の設計者であるエクスン・ツキノエは
...is her grandfather.
彼女の祖父だ
As you've heard, it's clear now that the Tower is a weapon.
聞いた通りもはや塔は明らかに兵器だ
Note: Next Departures
Hayate Komachi 19 - Will stop at: Morioka...
Yamabiko 59 - Will stop at: Kurikoma Plateau...
Over the past twenty-five years...
この25年ー
Note: Today's News: US Aircraft Carrier Independence Arrives in Tsugaru Bay. The UN Inspection Group...
...the Tower has become a part of the everyday
scenery and it symbolizes any number of things.
日常の風景に同化したあの塔は　あらゆるものの象徴だった
Note: Iwanami Bunko, Spring and Chaos, Written by Miyazawa Kenji
Nation. War. Race. Despair. Even admiration.
国家や載争や民族あるいは絶望や憧れ…
How it's interpreted differs between generations...
その受け止め方は世代によっても違う
But the one constant is that everyone sees it
as a symbol of something beyond their reach.
だが誰もが手の届かないものー
変えられないものの象徴として　見ているという点では同じだし
Something that can't be changed.
And as long as they do, this world probably won't change, either.
そう思っている以上この世界は変わらないだろう
Three days from now, early in the morning...
3日後の早朝にユニオンに対し
...the American government will declare war on the Union.
アメリカ政府からの宣戦布告が行われる
We're going to take advantage of the confusion caused by the war...
その開載の混乱に乗じ塔への爆破テロを行う
...and blow up the Tower.
We'll enter Ezo airspace with an unmanned Predator...
無人のブレデターでエゾに侵空
...and hit the Tower with a seeker
missile fitted with a PL outer-shell warhead.
攻撃にはPL外殼弾を載せたシーカーミサイルを使う
The Uilta Liberation Front will be disbanded on the same day.
ウィルク解放戦線は同日解散
As of now, this factory is shut down.
この工場も今日で閉鎖だ
Okay.
ああ
Okay, got it.
ああ分かったじゃあ明日な
See you tomorrow.
Hey.
よお
It's been three years, hasn't it, Takuya?
3年ぶりだなタクヤ
Note: Tokyo: City Tightens Security
When did you get here?
いつ来たんだ？
The day before yesterday.
おととい今は廃駅に泊り込んでるんだ
I've been sleeping in the abandoned station.
In the station?
廃駅に？
Yeah.
うんタクヤさその腕どうしたんだ？
What happened to your arm, Takuya?
Oh. Just a little accident.
ああちょっとな
What do you mean, an "accident"?
何だよちょっとって…
I'll tell you later.
…あとで話すよ
I guess it's closed again today.
今日も休みなのかな…
お！
Hey, Chobi!
チョビ元気だったか？久しぶりだなー
How are you?
It's been a while, huh?
You want to fly the Velaciela?
ヴェラシーラを飛ばす？
With Sawatari on board?
沢渡を乗せてか？
Yeah.
うん
Another day or so and I'll be done putting it together.
組み立てはあと一日もあれば終わるよ
All that's left will be the bug in the control software to deal with.
あとは
制御ソフトの問題だけど…
Wait a minute.
待てよおまえ俺の話聞いてたのか？
Did you even hear what I said?
Sawatari just stays asleep, and the Tower is...
沢渡は眠り続けているし塔は…
The Tower is going to be the target of the terrorist attack, right?
塔はテロの標的になってるんだろ？
That's why I need your help!
だからタクヤの助けが必要なんだよ
I told you already...
言っただろ　ずっと考えてたんだ
I've been thinking about it all the time.
If I fly her to the Tower, I think she'll wake up.
塔まで一緒に飛べば沢渡は目覚めると思うんだよ
You came back here for something like that?
…おまえ
そんなことのために帰ってきたのか？
"Something like that"?!
…そ
…そんなことって…約束したじゃないか俺たち
We made a promise!
I have a dream about Sawatari...
沢渡の夢を見るんだ
It repeats, over and over.
何度も繰り返し
She's by herself, in a place that's completely deserted.
沢渡は誰もいない場所に一人でいて
She says she can't remember anything.
何も思い出せないって言ってた
But she remembers the promise.
でもあいつ約束のことは覚えてる
I promised her again in the dream,
that I'd really take her to the Tower this time.
夢でもう一度　約束したんだよ今度こそ塔に連れてくって
I can't believe it's just a dream.
あれが…ただの夢とは思えないんだ
You come waltzing back into town...
…今さらのこのこやってきて
Here I was wondering what it was about, and you tell me it's about some dream?
何かと思えば夢の話か
You tick me off just looking at you.
お前を見てると苛々するよ
I don't have time for these games.
ガキの遊びに付き合ってるほどヒマじゃないぜ
The problem is you've been obsessed with something like this.
いつまでもこんなモノ1ご執着してるからだ
I'm gonna help you forget.
俺が忘れさせてやるよ
Don't!
…やめろ！
Takuya!
It's either save Sayuri...
サユリを救うのかー
...or save the world.
世界を救うのかだ
Note: Year 3, Class 3
Oh.
あちょっと忘れ物しちゃってさ…
I, uh, forgot something.
You did?
そうなんだ
Aren't you gonna go home, Sawatari?
沢渡帰らないのか？
Um, yeah.
あうん帰るよ
I will.
Hiroki-kun...
ヒロキ君
What happened to your cheek?
どうしたのほっべ
あ　ちょっと　タクヤとケンカしてさ
I kind of had a fight with Takuya.
Is everything okay?
大丈夫？
Yeah, it's fine.
大丈夫　大丈夫　きっとすぐ仲直りするんだ
We'll make up soon.
Probably.
たぶん
Okay. Good night.
じゃあな…おやすみ
Hiroki-kun!
ヒロキ君！ね駅まで行くの？
Are you going to the station?
Note: Girls Locker Room
I always have the feeling...
いつも予感があるの
...that I'm going to lose something.
何かをなくす予感
The world is so beautiful...
世界は本当に綺麗なのに
...but it's like I'm so far away from it... all alone.
私だけが
そこから遠く離れちゃってる気がするんだ
But to me...
でも僕にはその時ー
...Sayuri looked like she was at the center of the brilliant world.
サユリが輝く世界の中心にいるように見えたんだと思う
Ah, I see.
…ああそうか
I just felt like I sort of understood something very important...
今とても大切なことが
何か
...but it's gone...
…分かった気がしたのに…
Hello!
すいません！
Is anyone home?
誰かいませんか！
Okabe-san!
岡部さん
It's me, Hiroki.
ヒロキです岡部さん！
Okabe-san!
I can at least find out how to get hold of him.
運絡先だけでも…
うわっ！
Hiroki... I thought it was you.
…やっぱりヒロキかでかくなったな
You've grown.
Okabe-san?
…お岡部さん！？あのこれつて
Hey, what's this?
Takuya told me everything.
タクヤに聞いたぜ
Show me just how determined you are.
覚悟の程を見せてもらおうかな
You guys destroy the Tower.
オマエたちで塔を壊せよ
I wonder if the rumor about the terrorist bombings is true?
爆破テロの噂本当かしら
Who knows.
…どうでしようか　ただ開戦はもう目前だろうし
But the war is probably right about to begin...
And when it does,
researching the Tower could be the very last thing on our minds.
そうなれば塔の研究どころじやなくなるかもしれません
In terms of protesting the Separation...
…結局　ツキノエがしていることも
...I get the feeling that what Tsukinoe's doing...
ウィルタのようなテロ組織がしていることも
...is no different from terrorist organizations like Uilta.
南北分断への抗議って意味では
Note: Featured Article: The Menace of Terrorism
Opening Special article: The Union's Strategy
War Crisis, The Government's Silence, Data on the Latest Weapons on Both Sides
同じことなんじゃないかって気がします
You're a little mysterious, aren't you, Shirakawa-kun?
…白川君て　ちょっと不思議よね
I bet you have a lot of secrets.
何だか秘密が多いみたい
No.
イエそんなこと
Not at all...
Sorry.
ごめんお茶入れるねそれからー
I'll make some tea.
And let me take a look at that cheek, okay?
傷　手当てさせてね
Shirakawa-kun...
…白川君最近傷だらけだね
You get hurt a lot these days.
Sorry.
すいません…
Are you in trouble or something?
何か大変なこととかあるの？
No.
イエ
I'm fine.
大丈夫です
Sorry.
すいません…
He was my best friend.
…そいつ一番の友達だったんです
What?
え…
The one I had a fight with.
ケンカの相手です
We both longed for the same thing...
同じことに僅れて同じものを目指してました
We had the same goal...
うん…
But we went in different directions, and...
でも別々の場所に進んで何て言うか
How can I put this?
I was filled with an energy, a drive I didn't understand...
俺はどこに向かっていけばいいのか分からなくて
...but I ended up not knowing which way I should go.
わけの分からない力や衝動は
それでも体の中から溢れてくるのに
うん
That's why I was so relieved that I could join this research lab...
だからこの研究室に入れてすごく安心したんです
...because I felt like I had found something I should be doing.
やるべきことが見つかったような気がして
And...
それに…
I was also happy that I met you, Maki-san.
マキさんに会えたことも嬉しかった
That's why I don't want to involve you in this.
…だから
あなたを巻き込みたくないんです
There's something that I absolutely have to do.
どうしてもやらなきゃいけないことがあるんです
When it's all over...
全部終わったら
...I'd like to see you again.
俺もう一度マキさんに会いたいです
Shirakawa-kun!
白川君！
Sawatari...
沢渡
Let's go to the place we promised.
今度こそー
約束の場所に行こう
What's the big idea, Oka-chan?
どういうことだよ岡ちゃん
You're going to use kids for something like that?
子供をそんなことに利用するのか？
They're the ones who wanted to do it.
あいつらが望んだんだぜ
Besides, the area surrounding the Tower has
been swallowed up by those parallel world things, right?
それに塔の周りは
もともと平行宇宙とやらに飲み込まれてるんだろ
Not like anyone's gonna die there.
人死は出ねえよ
That's still no reason for...
だからってそんな…
Calm down, Tomizawa.
まあ落ち着けよ富澤
And anyway, by the time they get back, they won't be kids anymore.
それに帰ってくる頃にはアイツらも子供じゃないさ
You want me to guess what's going through your mind right now?
…お前が今考えていること当てようか？
Oh, geez...
ヤレヤレ…
Talk to you later.
じゃあ切るぜ
Looks like the final curtain's about to drop.
いよいよ大詰めだな
Is this really going to wake Sayuri-chan up?
サユリちやん　ホントにそれで目覚めるのか？
For some reason, I'm now convinced that it will.
俺も…なぜか今は罹信があるんです
The promise from that day is probably her link to reality.
あの日の約束がたぶん　沢渡の現実への絆なんです
Even now, in her dream, she's waiting for the Velaciela.
今も夢の中で　ヴェラシーラをずっと待ってる
I think both Hiroki and I sensed that somehow.
俺もヒロキもそれをどこかで感じ続けていたような気がします
The Velaciela is just a two-seater, and I can't pilot with this arm.
ヴェラシーラは二人乗りだしこの腕じゃ操縦はできないから
So, I'll stay behind and watch what happens to the Tower.
俺は残って塔の行方を見届けます
I thought it was cold. Now it's started snowing again.
冷えると思ったらまた降ってきやがった
Well, I'm leaving now.
それじゃ行きます
Yeah.
ああまあアレだ久しぶりのコンビなんだから
Well, then.
Hey, it's been a long time since you and Hiroki have worked together.
Be sure to get along now!
仲よくやれよ！
Which one is it?
どれだ？…これか！
This one?
Note: Wrong BIOS version. Check carefully, idiot!
You heard from Okabe-san?
岡部さんから聞いたか？
Yeah.
ああ…
Takuya!
…タクヤ
Which version of the BIOS should I use?
BlOSはどのバージョン使えばいいんだよ？
You changed the rudder location, didn't you?
途中でラダーの位置変えただろそれ以降のがないんだ
I still don't have the right one.
It's on this.
この中だ
It also has one for the seeker missile.
シーカーミサイルの分も入ってるから
What's left?
あと何が残ってるんだ？
I still have a little wiring of the superconducting motor.
超伝導モーターの配線が少しあとはソフトの微調整だけだよ
Other than that, there's just some fine tuning of the software.
They're scheduled to officially declare war in five hours.
宣戦布告予定まであと5時間
There's no other way but to fly right into the middle of the war.
その後の開戦にまぎれて　飛ぶしか手はないからな
I'll take care of the software.
ソフトは俺がやるから　ヒロキは配線を仕上げてくれ
You finish up the wiring.
Okay.
ああ…それからタクヤ！何だよあのエラーメッセージ
Hey, Takuya!
What the heck is with that error message?!
Huh?
え？
The one on version check.
バージョンチェックの
Version check?
バージョンチェック？
Ah!
…ああそこお前が組んだとこじゃないのか？
Didn't you write that thing three years ago?
3年前に
Huh?
あれそうだっけ…？
I did?
You haven't changed...
相変わらずだな…バカ
Idiot.
Hiroki, take a look at this.
ヒロキちょっと見てくれ
What is it?
なに？
The forecast of the battle conditions off the coast of Tsugaru.
津軽沖での戦闘状況予測が出たんだ
It's pretty much what we expected.
大体予想通りだ
So, the frontline will be up to about the 42nd latitude.
前線は42度線あたりまでか…
The inland area is virtually empty, especially around the Tower.
内陸部特に塔の周辺はガラアキだね
Well, the erosion has gotten pretty advanced on land.
地上は侵食が進んでるからなどう行く？
How do you want to go in?
Slip through flying low on the jet engine until we're clear of the strait.
海峡を抜けるまではジェットで低空をすり抜けて
We'll pass the 42nd latitude, and right around here...
42度線を抜けてココの山に差しかかったあたりで
...when we reach the mountains, I'll take her up to cruising altitude.
高度を取って巡航飛行…
How's that?
…こんなカンジでどうかな？
Yeah.
そうだな他にやりようもなさそうだ
I don't think there's any other way you could do it.
When you get to the Tower and Sawatari wakes up...
塔に着いたら沢渡の目覚めと前後して
...the disparate matter conversion on the ground should start again.
地上の異相変換が再開するはずだ
When that happens, get out of there fast.
そうなったらすぐに離脱して　塔から10キロ以上離れたら
Once you're about 10 km away from the Tower,
shoot the seeker missile.
シーカーミサイルを飛ばしてくれ
I programmed it, so that it will fly straight to the Tower.
自律飛行で塔まで飛ぶようにしてあるから
So, that's all you have to do. It will be over.
それですべて終わりだ
Yeah.
ああ大丈夫だよな
Everything will work out, right?
Yeah.
…ああ開戦まではまだ2時間近くある
There's still nearly two hours before the war starts.
We finished it earlier than we thought, huh?
思ったより早く仕上がったな
Yup.
うん…
Hiroki...
ヒロキ
Yeah?
ん？
By any chance...
もしかしてお前バイオリン弾けるのか？
Can you play the violin?
You're still a single-minded idiot, though.
…それにしてもさ
バカみたいに一途だよなぁオマエって
Who asked you?!
余計なお世話だぜオマエが頼んだんじゃねぇか…
Besides, you're the one who asked me to play!
Look over here and start playing!
こっち向いてやれよ
Shut up!
うるさいなあ！
Just shut your mouth and listen!
黙って聴けよ！
ははっ
I can tell my body's trembling...
目覚めの予感に体がふるえているのが分かる
It knows that I'm going to wake up.
Why is that?
どうしてだろう今は
I feel more afraid than anxious...
期待よりも恐れのほうが強い
Sayuri said,
"I always have the feeling that I'm going to lose something."
いつも何かをなくす予感があると
サユリはそう言った
I have a vague sense of that same feeling now.
今　僕もかすかに同じ予感を感じる
But...
でも
Just like I promised on that day after school...
いつかの放課後の約束ー
...I will go to that Tower.
あの塔まで私は行くんだ
The Tower's operational levels are rising again!
塔の稼動レベル再び上昇！
The branch universes' erosion area is expanding!
分岐宇宙の侵食範囲広がりつつあります
Current radius is 36 km and gradually
expanding at a rate of 0.4 km/hour.
現在半径約36キロ毎時0.4キロで
ゆっくりと拡大中です
Is this a reaction to the signs of her awakening?
目覚めの予兆に反応しているのか？
Everything will be okay, right, Oka-chan?
大丈夫なんだろうな岡ちゃん…
Professor!
先生！
War has just been declared!
今宣戦布告がなされました
The first conflict will soon take place off the coast of Tsugaru.
間もなく津軽沖で最初の衝突です
The land!
陸だ！
Sayuri, look.
ねえ
サユリ
It's the place of our promise.
約束の場所だよ
Those wings...
…あの翼
It's the Velaciela.
ヴェラシーラ…
あぁ…
The dreams... They're disappearing.
夢が消えてく…
I get it now.
ああ　そうか
I know now what I'm going to lose.
私がこれから何をなくすのか分かった
Oh, God...
…神さま
Please, God...
神さまどうか
Please wake Sayuri from her sleep.
サユリを眠りから覚まさせて下さい
どうか
Please, even if it's just for a moment after I wake up...
お願い…
目覚めてから一瞬だけでもいいの
Please don't make this feeling go away.
今の気持ちを消さないで下さい
I have to tell Hiroki-kun...
ヒロキ君に私は伝えなきゃ
...how special the connection we shared in our dreams was.
私たちの夢での心のつながりがどんなに特別なものだったか
I have to tell him how in a world with no one in it...
誰もいない世界で
私がどんなにヒロキ君を求めていて
...just how much I longed for him... and he longed for me.
ヒロキ君がどんなに私を求めていたか
Sayuri...
サユリ
Please...
お願い…！
I have to tell him how much I've loved him all this time.
私が今まで
どんなにヒロキ君のことを好きだったか
If I can just tell him that much...
それだけを伝えることができれば
...then I don't need anything else.
私は他には何もいりません
Please, even just for a moment...
どうか一瞬だけでも
Don't make this feeling go away!
この気持ちを…！
Sayuri...
サユリ…
Fujisawa-kun...
藤沢君…
Disparate matter conversion is rapidly expanding!
異相変換急速に拡大！
Ezo's being swallowed!
エゾが飲み込まれていきます！
Sayuri...
サユリ…
I...
わたし…
I have to tell you something...
わたし何かあなたに言わなくちゃ
Something very important...
とても大切な…
But now, it's gone!
…消えちゃった……！
It's all right.
…大丈夫だよ
You're awake now.
目が覚めたんだから
You can get it all back again, starting now.
これから全部また…
Welcome back, Sayuri.
おかえり
サユリ
iro aseta ao ni nijimu
The faded blue...
色あせた　青ににじむ
shiroi kumo tooi ano hi no iro
Blurred with the white clouds, the color of that distant day.
白い雲　遠いあの日のいろ
kokoro no oku no dare nimo
In the depths of my heart...
心の奥の誰にも
kakushiteru itami
Lies a pain I hide from everyone.
隠してる痛み
boku no subete kaketa
The words on which I pledged my all...
僕のすべてかけた
kotoba mou tooku
Are now in the distant past.
言葉　もう遠く
nakusu hibi no naka de ima mo
In the days since you've gone...
なくす日々の中で今も
きみは僕を　あたためてる
kimi wa boku wo atatameteru
You still give me warmth.
We've lost the place of our promise in this world...
約束の場所をなくした世界で　それでもー
...but even so...
...our lives begin now.
これから　僕たちは生きはじめる
kimi no koe kimi no katachi terashita hikari
The light illuminated your voice... your form.
きみのこえ
きみのかたち　照らした光
かなうなら
kanau nara
If possible...
僕のこえ
boku no koe dokoka no kimi
I'll live in a way that my voice will reach you...
どこかのきみ　とどくように
todoku youni boku wa ikiteku
No matter where you are.
僕は生きてく
hizashi ni yaketa reeru kara
The sounds echo distantly...
日差に灼けた　レールから
hibiku oto tooku ano hi no koe
From those sun-baked rails, it's the voice of the day.
響くおと　遠く　あの日のこえ
ano kumo no mukou ima demo
Even now, the promised place exists...
あの雲のむこう　今でも
yakusoku no basho aru
Beyond those clouds.
約束の場所　ある
いつからか孤独　僕を
itsu kara ka kodoku boku wo
I don't know since when, but solitude surrounds me...
kakomi kishimu kokoro
And my heart creaks under the strain.
囲み　きしむ心
sugiru toki no naka de kitto
I'm certain that as time passes...
過ぎる　時の中できっと
boku wa kimi wo nakushiteyuku
I will lose you.
僕はきみを　なくしていく
kimi no kami sora to kumo tokashita sekai
Your hair... in a world in which the clouds and sky melt.
きみの髪
空と雲　とかした世界
himitsu ni michite
It's full of mysteries.
秘密に満ちて
きみのこえ
kimi no koe yasashii yubi kaze ukeru hada
Your voice, gentle fingers and skin that caught the wind.
やさしい指　風うける肌
kokoro tsuyoku suru
It bolsters my heart.
こころ強くする
kimi no koe kimi no katachi terashita hikari
The light illuminated your voice... your form.
きみのこえ
きみのかたち　照らした光
かなうなら
kanau nara
If possible...
生きる場所
ikiru basho chigau keredo
Though we live in different worlds...
違うけれど　優しく強く
yasashiku tsuyoku bokuwa ikitai
I want to live kind and strong.
僕は生きたい
Fin